A Guide to the Papers of the Cook Family 1872-1976
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Cook Family Papers 1872-1976
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 46
6 Hollinger Boxes and 1 Hollinger Documents Case.
Freeman Cook
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
The family of Henry Clarico Freeman Cook, the donor of the Cook Family Papers, dates to several distinguished Virginians. The family traces its ancestry to Richard Blow, a dominant figure in the business life of eighteenth and nineteenth century Virginia. The papers of Richard Blow are with the Blow Family Papers in the manuscripts collection of the Library of the College of William and Mary. Richard Blow's grandson, George Blow Jr., was a Norfolk judge and a member of the state convention for Virginia's secession at the time of the Civil war. Judge George Blow and his wife, Elizabeth Taylor Allmand, settled on Boush Street in Norfolk, where their daughter, Emma, grew up. Blow Street in Norfolk is named after this family.
Emma Blow married Arthur Clarico Freeman and they had three children, Arthur II, Elizabeth Allmond ("Lizzie"), and Emma. It is this generation and their descendants which the Cook Family Papers detail.
Arthur II was born in 1878 and graduated from Virginia Military Institute in 1897. His interest in engineering led him to several inventions, some of which he attempted to sell to the government during World Wars I and II. He married a woman named Elsa, of whom his family disapproved, forcing Arthur to leave Norfolk and settle in Pennsylvania. In 1924, Elsa died and Arthur returned to Norfolk with his four children. In the 1950's, Arthur carried on much correspondence with Katherine Groner Shropshire who resided in New York and later in St. Augustine, Florida. Her letters to Arthur are quite revealing; unfortunately the collection contains few letters from Arthur to Katherine.
Of Arthur's children, the collection reveals information only about his daughter, Elfrieda Blow Freeman ("Elf"). Elfrieda married Merton B. Tice and settled in Mitchell, South Dakota. Tice was active in state politics and Elfrieda became National President of the Ladies Auxiliary of the Veterans of Foreign Wars in 1963. They had three children, Charles, Baird, and Virginia.
The collection reveals little information about Elizabeth Allmond Freeman ("Lizzie"). Lizzie founded the Edgewater Garden Club and lived in the family home in the Edgewater subdivision of Norfolk with her sister, Emma, until her death.
Emma Blow Freeman married Allen Merriam Cook and they initially settled in the family home on Boush Street. They had three children; Allen Blow, and twins, Henry Clarico Freeman ("Freeman") and Clarice.
The bulk of the collection consists of the papers of Allen M. Cook. He graduated from the U.S. Naval Academy in 1893 and served in the Navy until 1919, retiring with the rank of commander. Allen M. Cook's Naval career took him to assignments throughout the United States, while his wife remained in Norfolk. Emma Freeman Cook was active in the Edgewater Garden Club and the Great Bridge Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution. Upon his retirement, Commander Cook carried on a large real estate business in Norfolk. When he died in 1941, his widow continued to live at the family's home in Edgewater until her death in 1956.
Allen Blow Cook was born in 1899 and graduated from the U.S. Naval Academy in 1921. A physical disability caused him to retire in 1926. He received his masters degree in 1929 from the University of Virginia and joined the faculty at the Naval Academy. In 1942, he was recalled to active duty and retired in 1947 with the rank of commander. Upon retirement he returned to the Naval Academy faculty. He died in 1971.
The twins, Henry Clarico Freeman ("Freeman") and Clarice, were born in 1909. The collection contains little information of Clarice, other than a few references in the family's correspondence. She married Arthur Gardner and settled in New York.
At the time this biography was written, Freeman Cook, the donor of the collection, was living in St. Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands. Though he received a scholarship to Virginia Polytechnic Institute, his family wished him to attend the University of Virginia, where he would be a "gentleman." He did attend UVA and studied agriculture. He later traveled and worked throughout the U.S. and in Panama, where he met his wife, Pepita.
Freeman enlisted in the Navy, though the collection only reveals that in 1944 he was a Chief Petty Officer stationed in Norfolk.
The Cook Family is perhaps most notable for their residence, The Tazewell House, in the Edgewater subdivision of Norfolk. Once the home of Littleton Waller Tazewell, a U.S. Senator and Governor of Virginia in the nineteenth century, the mansion was originally located at Granby and Boush Streets in Norfolk. When the mansion- was threatened in the early twentieth century, Emma Blow Freeman (Mrs. Arthur Clarico Freeman) purchased the house, and had it dismantled and reassembled on a site facing the Elizabeth River in Edgewater. According to a newsclipping in the collection, even the trees on the original site were uprooted and replanted at the new location. The Cook Family lived in the home at least until 1960's. Today, the privately owned Tazewell House is on the National Register of Historic Places.
Scope and Content Information
The Cook Family Papers, dating from 1872 to 1976, include material documenting the lives of the children of Arthur Clarico and Emma Blow Freeman, and later generations. Most of the collection centers on the personal and business papers of Allen Merriam Cook. The collection documents a prominent Norfolk family, the development of subdivisions in Norfolk and Virginia Beach, and the career of a Naval Officer from 1889 - 1919.
Organization
The papers are divided into ten series: correspondence; minutes and proceedings; diaries; printed material; financial documents; photographic material; literary productions; legal documents; scrapbooks and scrapbook material; and charts, diagrams, lists, real estate plats, and maps.
Series I: Correspondence
In the correspondence series, separate subseries are established for each member of the family and for Harry A. Seawell, a business associate of Allen M. Cook. There is also a subseries for miscellaneous addresses, postcards, and stationery.
There is some interesting correspondence between Arthur Clarico Freeman II and the War Department concerning an invention Arthur wished to sell. One such letter is from Josephus Daniels, Secretary of the Navy. The incoming and outgoing correspondence of Allen Merriam Cook concerning his Naval career covers his service record. This contains a notice on April 19, 1889, to report to the U.S. Naval Academy for an appointment examination and a letter from Josephus Daniels.
Unless otherwise noted, it should be assumed all letters are written by the individual in the subseries under which they are filed.
Series II: Minutes and Proceedings
Items of special interest in this series are the minutes and proceedings of the Princess Anne and Norfolk Mutual Building and Loan Association.
Series III: Diaries
This series includes a diary kept by Naval Cadet Allen Merriam Cook while at sea aboard the U.S.S. Newark, as required by his commanding officer, and a diary kept by Emma Freeman Cook.
Series IV: Printed Material
Of special interest in this series is a printed poem, "Old Christ Church," by Emma Blow Freeman, and a magazine, "Know the Navy and Norfolk," in which, on page 144-E, Allen Merriam Cook is profiled. Also included in this series are miscellaneous newspaper and magazine clippings, pamphlets, circulars, flyers, and programs. There are interesting references to real estate development in Norfolk and Virginia Beach among the newspaper clippings and circulars.
Series V: Financial Documents
This series contains real estate account books; miscellaneous reports, forms, and receipts; and miscellaneous handwritten notes pertaining to real estate and the Princess Anne and Norfolk Mutual Building and Loan Association.
Series VI: Photographic Material
Photographs in this series are classified under the pertinent family member. In addition, there are subseries containing photographs and negatives of miscellaneous or unknown people and places. There is a cut profile of an unknown man in subseries I. Many of the photographs have notes on the reverse identifying people or places.
Series VII: Literary Productions
This series contains drafts of various documents, both business and personal, essays, memoirs, clippings and copies of poetry, recipes, reminiscences, reports, research notes, and speeches. Of special interest are such items as a document, similar to a resume, of Arthur Clarico Freeman II, entitled, "Professional Record -Education Experience," an account of an apparently false arrest of Lizzie Freeman, a series of reports prepared by Allen Merriam Cook while in the Navy, and an evaluation by his commanding officer of Allen Merriam Cook while serving on the U.S.S. Amphitrite.
Series VIII: Legal Documents
Legal documents are divided into Allen Merriam Cook's business documents and the family's personal documents. Of special interest is a copy of the Certificate of Incorporation of the Princess Anne and Norfolk Mutual Building and Loan Association, and several various papers of the Princess Anne and Norfolk Mutual Building and Loan Association and the Ferndale Corporation, in which Allen Merriam Cook was also involved. Also in this series is a copy of Henry Clarico Freeman Cook's birth certificate.
Series IX: Scrapbooks and Scrapbook Material
Of special interest in this series are two scrapbooks kept by Allen Merriam Cook, filled with newspaper clippings relating to the U.S. military. This series also contains a drawing of unknown origin, signed with the initials, "G.B." The only family members with such initials were Richard Blow's son, George, or George Blow, Jr.
Series X: Artifacts
Includes the Foreign Legion cap of Allen Merriam Cook, a picture of a sailboat, international code flag cards, a picture signed by G.B., and an unidentified key.
Series XI: Charts, Lists, Diagrams, Real Estate Plats, Maps
Included in this series are various charts, diagrams of property, lists of subdivision owners, real estate plats, and miscellaneous maps of the Norfolk area, the U.S., and Europe. Included among the charts is the itinerary of Elfrieda Freeman Tice's tour of the U.S. on behalf of the Ladies Auxiliary of the Veterans of Foreign Wars. The many real estate plats of the Norfolk and Virginia Beach area should be of value to anyone interested in the development of area subdivisions.
Series XII: Genealogy
Genealogical material and information compiled by Allen Merriam Cook about the Cook Family's history.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Arthur Clarico Freeman II
    - General Correspondence October 1917-March 1963 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Inventions, World War I May-August 1917 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Inventions, World War II December 1939-August 1950 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Katherine Groner Shropshire (incoming) January 1951-April 1958 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Katherine Groner Shropshire (outgoing) March 1952-February 1956 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Undated (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Elizabeth Allmond Freeman
    - Correspondence received (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Emma Blow Freeman Cook
    - General Correspondence (outgoing) August 1907-January 1943 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence (incoming) August 1909-May 1953 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - From Edmund S. Ruffin and Sons, Counsellors at Law (incoming) September 1942-December 1955 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - From James G. Martin and Sons, Attorneys at Law (incoming) March 1950-October 1951 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Allen Merriam Cook
    - Correspondence July 1898-April 1939 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence with his sons, Allen Blow and Henry Clarico Freeman Cook (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Business, Financial, Legal 1902, 1913, 1916-1919 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-December 1921 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January 1922-December 1923 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Business, Financial, Legal July-December 1924 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-December 1925 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-December 1926 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-December 1927 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-November 1928 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-November 1929 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January 1930-December 1932 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Business, Financial, Legal February-April 1933 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Business, Financial, Legal May-December 1933 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-March 1934 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Business, Financial, Legal April-May 1934 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Business, Financial, Legal July-November 1934 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Business, Financial, Legal Febrary-October 1935 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-October 1936 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-April 1937 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Business, Financial, Legal May 1937 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Business, Financial, Legal July-December 1937 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Business, Financial, Legal June-November 1938 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Business, Financial, Legal April-December 1939 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-December 1940 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Business, Financial, Legal January-April 1941, February 1949, November 1953 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Naval Correspondence April 1889-December 1895 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Naval Correspondence August 1896-November 1898 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Naval Correspondence February-June 1899 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Naval Correspondence August-December 1899 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Naval Correspondence March 1900-July 1901 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Naval Correspondence September 1901-April 1902 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Naval Correspondence June-September 1902 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Naval Correspondence January 1903-October 1904 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Naval Correspondence April-October 1905 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Naval Correspondence May-November 1906 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Naval Correspondence July-October 1907 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Naval Correspondence January-November 1908 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Naval Correspondence February-October 1909 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Naval Correspondence January-December 1910 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Naval Correspondence March-December 1911 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Naval Correspondence December 1916, October 1937, September 1939 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Miscellaneous and undated Correspondence (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Harry A. Seawell
    - Business, Financial, Legal November 1917-July 1929 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Elfrieda Blow Freeman Tice
    - Correspondence August 9, 1920; September 1962-March 1963 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Merton B. Tice
    - Correspondence May 20, 1958; June-July 1961 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Allen Blow Cook
    - Family and Naval Correspondence 1929-1965 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Henry Clarico Freeman Cook
    - Family and Business Correspondence 1930-1976 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Christmas Cards received (n.d.) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Pepita B. Cook
    - General Correspondence September 1975, April 28, 1976 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Financial, Business, Legal (Letters in Spanish) January-December 1971 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Financial, Business, Legal January-December 1972; January-March 1975 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Address, Phone Numbers, Blank Mailing Label (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Blank Postcards and Cards (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Blank Stationary and Paper (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 67)
- Minutes and Proceedings
  - Minutes, Vestry Meeting, Christ and St. Luke's Church March 13, 1974 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Constitution, Edgewater Garden Club (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Minutes, Meeting of Great Bridge Chapter, D.A.R. May 8, 1943 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Princess Anne & Norfolk Mutual Building & Loan Association January 1935-May 1937 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 71)
  - By-Laws, Princess Anne & Norfolk Mutual Building & Loan Association, Inc. (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Norfolk Federal Savings and Loan re: Merger (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Federal Savings and Loan Association re: Merger (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 74)
- Diaries
  - Allen Merriam Cook re: Naval Service July 1893-March 1895 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Allen Merriam Cook June - July 1906 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Emma Freeman Cook, House Expenses Ledger 1924 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
- Printed Material
  - Applications
    - Assistant Scoutmaster's Application, Henry Clarico Freeman Cook May 1927 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Books
    - Choice Recipes 1907 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Handbook of Christ Church, Philadelphia (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Christmas Cards (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
    - English/German Dictionary (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
    - A Few Recipes From Virginia (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Flags of America (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Foreign Policy, Number 8 1972 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Healing Christ by Henry Victor Morgan (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Information Booklet on Foreign Ports Visited, Allen M. Cook (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 11)
    - League of Nations - Organization for Communications (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Spots or 202 Cleansers, compiled by Clarice T. Courvoisier (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Unigraph: An Improved Method of Verbatim Reporting (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Certificates and Diplomas
    - Civic Beautification Committee, Oklahoma City, OK, H.C. Freeman Cook April 7, 1941 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Diploma de Honor, H.C. Freeman Cook May 1951 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Ministerio de Agricultura, Comercio e Industrias, Pepita B. Cook January 1959 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Office of Superintendent of School, H.C. Freeman Cook July 1929 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Prescription, H.C. Freeman Cook January 1977 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 18)
    - U.S. Public Health Service Hospital, Lizzie Freeman February 1952 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Circulars, Flyers, Programs
    - History of the Cook Family; Cook Family News June 1902, January 1904 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Ladies Auxiliary of Veterans of Foreign Wars, Elfrieda Blow Freeman Tice 1955-1963 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous April 1913-Winter 1975 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous (n.d.) (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Magazine and Magazine Clippings
    - American Cookery January 1925 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Home Economist 1929 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Know the Navy and Norfolk August 1944 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Know Tidewater Virginia October 1942 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 26)
    - SKETCH, Iowa State College December 1936 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 27)
    - The Quarterdeck April 1946 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Seagoing Language" by Allen Blow Cook January 1937 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Salty Lingo" by Allen Blow Cook September 1955 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Miscellaneous Clippings 1872-1899 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous Clippings 1901-1954 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Miscellaneous Clippings, A-M (not dated) (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Miscellaneous Clippings, N-Z (not dated) (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Photograph of Allen Merriam Cook, Emma Blow Freeman (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Articles and Photographs re: Elfrieda Blow Freeman Tice and Family 1950-1963 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Articles re: Arthur Clarico Freeman II (not dated) (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Letter to the Editor, Lizzie Freeman May 1938 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Articles re: Family History (Boush-Tazewell-Waller House) 1941-1977 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Articles and Pictures re: Henry Clarico Freeman Cook May 1921-January 1977 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Articles re: Business and Real Estate 1914-1923 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Articles re: News Events 1920-1970 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Miscellaneous Articles 1916-1955 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Miscellaneous Articles (not dated) (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Pamphlets, Booklets, Catalogs
    - "Sketch of Annapolis Lodge, No. 622" The Elks Club (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 45)
    - "Unique in the Republic" 1826 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Official Program, Yorktown Sesquicentennial Celebration 1931 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Catechisms (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Daughters of the American Revolution, Great Bridge Chapter (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Edgewater Garden Club (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Flag of the United States (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Landscaping, Gardening (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Local History (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Prayers, Church History (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Provident Mutual Life Insurance Company (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Recipes (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
    - World Peace (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Poetry
    - "Old Christ Church" Emma Blow Freeman (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
- Financial Documents
  - Account Books
    - Virginia Beach Property August 18, 1925 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Order Book, Coleman Place (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Journal Coleman Annex (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Record of Buyers and Rent (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Journal, Ferndale Corp. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Notebook, Allen M. Cook (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Journal of Listings, Book #3 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Emma Blow Freeman Cook (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Documents and Receipts
    - Allen M. Cook, General, 11 folders (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 18-Folder 28)
    - Allen M. Cook - Army and Navy Club Annual Reports 1932-1933 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Allen M. Cook - Bird Neck Point, Virginia Beach (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Allen M. Cook - Examiner's Reports, Princess Anne & Norfolk Building and Loan Association 1933 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Allen M. Cook - Reports of Audits July 1928-March 1932, 2 folders (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 32-33)
    - Allen M. Cook - Reports of Expenditures, St. Julienne's Creek, VA, Naval Magazine (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 34)